Hartford Women's Center Papers GLBTQ.2012.01
GLBTQ Archives, Central Connecticut State University
Hartford Women's Center Papers
1970-2003
GLBTQ.2012.01
GLBTQ Archives, Central Connecticut State University
2.5 Linear feet
The Hartford Women’s Center (HWC) was organized in October of 1977 to serve women of the city of Hartford. The goal was to create network of organizations with resources for women. Newsletters and calendars were ways to reach out to community. HWC helped to establish first Hartford Feminist Library in 1979. The collection consists of newsletters, minutes, flyers, photographs and slides and extensive correspondence.
Irene, Scheibner
Biographical/Historical note
The Hartford Women’s Center (HWC) was organized in October of 1977. The first meeting was held as an open discussion to talk about the creation of a place for women in the city. Fifty women attended that meeting and expressed ideas about wanting social activities, referral services, support groups, art classes, sports, and coordination for all these activities and an emotionally supportive environment. The goal of the center was then to create a network for existing women’s organizations as well as identify new community resources for women and provide a communications network through newsletters and a calendar. Meetings, library space, and social gathering space were held at the Hill Center of Hartford, 350 Farmington Avenue. As part of the Hartford Women’s Project, they shared offices with 13 other women’s organizations at 57 Pratt Street in the city. Irene Scheibner, member of the Hartford Women’s Center and Central Connecticut State University alumni, founded the Hartford Feminist Library in 1979. The library’s purpose was to provide books, periodicals, and information by and about women to the greater Hartford community. The collection housed books regarding topics such as women’s history, women and political theory, Black and Hispanic women, women artists, poets, authors, and non-sexist children’s books.
Scope and Contents note
Subject files, correspondence, notes, flyers, printed material, posters, photographs, newspapers articles, periodicals. 1917; 1970-2003
Other Finding Aids note
Restrictions: Access to financial records restricted until 2015.
Feminism -- United States -- History; Feminism -- United States -- Periodicals; Feminism -- United States -- Societies, etc; Women -- America -- History; Women -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Women politicians -- United States
- “Cobra Lilly & Her Renegade Nuns” in New England Connexion, January, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Connecticut Lesbian and Gay Pride Festival, March, and Concert- Program, 10 photographs, 20 negatives, June 23, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence with Irene Scheibner, CCSU Foundation, Frank Gagliardi regarding monetary gift from the Hartford Feminist Library to Burritt Library, 1999/2000; Hartford Feminist Collection donation from HWC, 1999, list of items; donor forms, 1997; Correspondence regarding donations to CCSU, 1997., 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cruise Deep River Navigation Company- Charter agreement with HWC, cruise map, June 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dollar for Doers Grant Application Aetna, description of grant request, November 16, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ella Grasso: campaign advertisements, resignation, December 5, 1980, death and funeral newspaper ads, February 6 – 10, March 4, 1981., 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hartford Feminist Library- Publicity, flyers and articles about programs, 1979, 1981-1985; greeting card upon closing, 1989., 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hartford Feminist Library- Application for Hay market Grant, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hartford Feminist Library- Checking account statements, People’s Bank., 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hartford Feminist Library- Statement of Policy, Library procedures, financial accounts 1979 – 1986, Reserve Book List. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hartford Feminist Library- 1979-1987 Volunteers Group photograph. Photography taken by Irene Scheibner (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hartford Women’s Center- Annual Election Meeting of the Board of Directors Minutes, 1984, 1985, 1987, 1988, 1990, 1992, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hartford Women’s Center and Feminist Library- Bylaws- Draft and final. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hartford Women’s Center and Feminist Library- Certificate of Dissolution, November 28, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hartford Women’s Center checkbook registers and check 11/3/1984 – 6/5/1990; 11/22/1996 – 2/21/2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Hartford Women’s Center and Feminist Library- Incorporation and tax exempt documents., 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Hartford Women’s Collective- Incorporation Document, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Hartford Women’s Center- Anniversary editions, histories, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18Hartford Women’s Center- Tax Returns and other tax matters, 1978 – 1985)
- Hartford Women’s Center- Tax Returns and other tax matters, 1978 – 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Hartford Women’s Center and Feminist Library Tenth Anniversary- Group photograph taken by Irene Scheibner, November 15, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Hartford Women’s Center Treasurer’s Ledger- 3/3/1978 – 6/8/1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hartford Women’s Center Treasurer’s Ledger- 6/23/1981 – 12/30/1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Hartford Women’s Center Treasurer’s Ledger- 1/25/1986 – 10/31/1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Hartford Women’s Center Treasurer’s Ledger- 11/2/1988 – 3/30/1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Hartford Women’s Center Treasurer’s Ledger- 4/2/1991- 12/7/1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- International Women’s Day for Disarmament-Flyer, Hartford, May 24 (no year) Spanish version on reverse. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Lesbian Convergence-Presented by HWC- booklets, flyers, schedules. 1986, 1988, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- “Lesbian Literature Catalog Giovanni’s Room”, Fall, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- “Lesbian Uneasy in Northampton” by Kristi Vaughan, in Hartford Courant, August 7, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Library Auction Fundraisers- notes, advertisements, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Library forms (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Mentzer, Melissa, A., Founders Awards, Introduction for Irene Scheibner December 12, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Scheibner, Irene, Inventory of donation of materials to the Burritt Library, July 16, 2002; list of items, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat- Program, September 5 – 7, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat Encore- Program, flyer, September 3 – 6, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat III- Program flyer, “Directory of Festival Craftswimmin,” September 2 – 5, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat IV- Program, August 31 – September 3, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat V- Directory of Retreat Craftswomen, Program, August 30 – September 2, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat VII- Program, directory of craftswomen, September 4 – 7, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- New England Women’s Musical Retreat VIII- Program, map, directory of craftswomen September 2 – 5, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Rich, Adrienne “Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence” in Signs, Summer 1980. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Women Against Nuclear Power Fundraising Concert- Twelve color slides of women performers at event, 1980’s. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Women’s Liberation Sticker 10 x 10 cm. orange and blue - Clenched fist inside international symbol for women (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Women March to Take Back the Night- Program, New Haven, July 28, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Women’s Right of Spring [Camping Weekend] Flyers for 1979, 1980, 1981, 1984, 1985 and 1990 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Russian Women Poetry Movement, Ms. Magazine, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Women in San Francisco, Flyers, 1987 [34 different flyers] (Box 1, Folder 47)
- “A Simple Matter of Justice” 1993 March on Washington program guide sticker, postcard, flyer. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- West Side Waltz- Playbill and ticket stubs, 1982; Women’s Music for Everyone-Program and flyer, 1982; Stonewall Rebellion, 12th anniversary, New York, June 28, 1981, purple armband? 13.5 x 36 cm; Ole’ Octopus, Ole Coordinating Committee, May 1985., 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Near, Holly, photograph, 20 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Meg Christian / Cris Williamson at Carnegie Hall- Playbill, November 26, 1982. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- New England Blizzard (women’s professional basketball team) - Two cards autographed by the team, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Navratilova, Martina - articles., 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Connecticut Falcons Official Game Program- Women’s softball team., 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Colorado Silver Bullets- Women’s baseball team yearbooks., 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Women’s professional softball, official program., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Women’s Sports, Title IX Correspondence., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- World Champion Connecticut Falcons- official yearbook., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- NCAA The Road to the Final Four, 1999 Women’s Final Four chart (Box 1, Folder 59)
- ITT Hartford “Maybe your daughter will get recruited by UCONN” autographed by Jennifer Rizzotti, n.d (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Connecticut Yearbook Media Guide (Women’s Basketball), 1993-94, 1994-95, ticket stub, newspaper photo copies. (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Connecticut District Postal Team Salutes the UCONN Women’s Basketball Team. Special Cancellations to mark 1995 National Women’s Basketball Champions, April 2, 1995 3 postcards in special folder, 3 envelopes. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Storybook Ending… (UConn Women’s Basketball Team Win 1995 National Championship) in Sports Illustrated, April 10, 1995. 3 copies autographed by Jennifer Rizzotti. (Box 1, Folder 63)
- “UConn 35 – 0, The Championship Season,” Hartford Courant, 1995 and photograph (Box 1, Folder 64)
- UConn Women’s Basketball Game Programs., 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Webber, Pam, UConn Women’s basketball player. (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Montague, Jill, Teddy… a memoir [1996] typescript (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Uncensored Magazine, June 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- “Katherine Hepburn, American Classic” Ladies Home Journal Special, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Periodicals with articles related to women in sports 1982-1994- Tennis Magazine, July, 1993 & November, 1994; Women’s Sports, August, 1977 & September, 1982; “100 Greatest Female Athletes of the Century” from Sports Illustrated for Women, 81-86, n.d.; “Dottie Mochrie” in Fairway, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- “Remarkable American Women” Life., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Women’s Space, v. 4 no 1, 1999; “Lesbian Chic” New York, May 10, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- “Women of the year” MS., January, 1986; “A ride in space”, Sally Ride, People, June 20, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Woman Citizen, The Woman’s Journal, October 6, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ms. 15th anniversary issue. July/August, 1987; Ms. Women of the Year, January, 1987. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Ms. 20th anniversary issue. July/August, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  General note
  Ms. The world of Women is a magzine publisehd in NYC, its contenct relates to women's issues: feminism, health, art, publishing, sexuality, etc.
- Holland, Nancy- Miscellaneous writings. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous brochures, articles relating to women’s issues and events- Women's Equality Day, Women's retreat in New York, Lesbian Convergence (8 photos of women at the tables). (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Hartford Women’s Center Tenth Anniversary- Celebration album: 15 pages of inscriptions. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- HWC cancelled checks #1, 2, 3, 1978; checks 101 – 487, 1978 – 1984; deposit stamp (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Women in Hartford Newsletters, May, 1978 – June, 1981 organized in black binder (Box 2, Oversize 3)
- Stonewall Means Fight Back, Smash Lesbian & Gay Oppression, Washington, D.C. October 14, 1979, Banner 29 x 37cm. (Box 3, Object 1)
- Brown, Rita Mae, framed colored photograph by Paula Bronstein of the Hartford Courant., 1988 (Box 3, Object 2)
- “Sisterhood is powerful” bumper sticker. (Box 3, Object 3)
- “She is risen” (1972 Mana) bumper sticker (Box 3, Object 4)
- Pinnacle cards, 1998; Silver Bullets women baseball player cards. [28 cards] 1995?; Women basketball player cards [14 cards] skybox, 1999; Women basketball player cards [ 20 cards] (Box 3, Object 5)
- Supersisters cards (72 cards)., 1979 (Box 3, Object 6)
- “Library Sweet Library”, carved wood plaque, In celebration of the 5th anniversary of the Hartford feminist Library, 1984, carved by Joseph A. Knapp? 23 x 36cm. (Box 3, Object 7)
- Framed article, “Feminist Library Plans Expansion of its Services” by Stephan Sevick of The Hartford Courant, n.d. (Box 3, Object 8)
- Framed drawing of 2 women, ones kneeled down and the other reaching up towards a sun, 32.5 x 42 cm. (Box 3, Object 9)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v.1., 1970-1977 (Box 4, Object 1)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v.2., 1975-1977 (Box 4, Object 2)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v.3, 1977 – 1978 (Box 4, Object 3)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v. 4 3/27/1978 – 6/5/1978 (Box 4, Object 4)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v. 5, 6/1/1978 - 1/14/1979 (Box 4, Object 5)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v. 6, 1/13/1979 – 11/29/1979 (Box 4, Object 6)
- Hartford Women’s Center Press Books / Scrapbooks- v. 7, 9/7/1979 – 2001. (Box 4, Object 7)
- The Winner by Norman Rockwell (Box 4, Object 8)
- “Inside Women’s Tennis” poster., 1990 (Box 4, Object 9)
- 20 Buttons related to Hartford Women’s Center and Library (Box 4, Object 1)